<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pages on Avi Vaid</title>
    <link>http://avaid96.github.io/page/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pages on Avi Vaid</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 23:41:46 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://avaid96.github.io/page/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>principles</title>
      <link>http://avaid96.github.io/principles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 23:41:46 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://avaid96.github.io/principles/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;reflections&#34;&gt;Reflections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Worrying only makes you struggle twice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the opportunities and obligations of power&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on relationships, not networking (David Rockefeller)

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;remember what people tell you and ask them about it next time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t look for something out of an interaction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pressure is not stress. But the former is converted to the latter when you add one ingredient: rumination, the tendency to keep rethinking past or future events, while attaching negative emotion to those thoughts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Listen instead of focusing on questioning in an argument - try to get the best outcome not prove yourself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enjoy the present but care for your future self&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://m.economictimes.com/news/politics-and-nation/billionaire-sends-son-to-hyderabad-to-face-lifes-struggles/real-life-internship/slideshow/60208598.cms&#34;&gt;http://m.economictimes.com/news/politics-and-nation/billionaire-sends-son-to-hyderabad-to-face-lifes-struggles/real-life-internship/slideshow/60208598.cms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple living, high thinking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not what you don&amp;rsquo;t know that gets you in trouble but what you know that just ain&amp;rsquo;t so (Twain)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just because you are doing a lot doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you&amp;rsquo;re getting a lot done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not all who wander are lost&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;It is very dangerous when you don&amp;rsquo;t know what you want&amp;hellip; but you know what is expected of you. I&amp;rsquo;ve had enough of doing the latter.&amp;rdquo;
Since then I&amp;rsquo;ve always asked myself: am I doing what I want&amp;hellip; or what is expected of me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even your shadow leaves you in the darkness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.potw.org/archive/potw232.html&#34;&gt;http://www.potw.org/archive/potw232.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is only one thing that makes a dream impossible to achieve: the fear of failure. (Alchemist)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never test the depth of the water with both feet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When something bad happens, you have 3 choices, let it define/destroy/strengthen you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The greeks has two meanings for &amp;lsquo;utopia&amp;rsquo;. &amp;lsquo;Uo-Topos&amp;rsquo; = Good Place and &amp;lsquo;Ou-Topos&amp;rsquo; = Place that you cannot be&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everybody wants to go to heaven but nobody wants to die - US Navy Seals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep people&amp;rsquo;s bellies full and balls empty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The way I think about it, luck is like a bernoulli random variable and p is a function of hard work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will always be too much of something for someone: Too big, Too loud, Too edgy. If you round out your edges, You Lose Your Edge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are willing to do only whats easy, life will be hard. But if you are going to do whats hard, life will be easy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any sufficiently advanced technology is indistinguishable from magic - Arthur Clarke&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sapiens&#34;&gt;Sapiens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Family and community are replaced by state and market&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;art-of-war&#34;&gt;Art of war&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you plunder a countryside, let the spoil be divided amongst your men; when you capture new territory, cut it up into allotments for the benefit of the soldiery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you surround an army, leave an outlet free. Don&amp;rsquo;t press a desperate foe too hard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your opponent is of choleric temper, seek to irritate him. Pretend to be weak, that he may grow arrogant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no instance of a country having benefited from prolonged warfare.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He will win who

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;knows when to fight and when not to fight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;knows how to handle both superior and inferior forces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;army is animated by the same spirit throughout all its ranks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;prepared himself, waits to take the enemy unprepared.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has military capacity and is not interfered with by the sovereign.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thus the good fighter is able to secure himself against defeat, but cannot make certain of defeating the enemy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thus it is that in war the victorious strategist only seeks battle after the victory has been won, whereas he who is destined to defeat first fights and afterwards looks for victory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When in difficult country, do not encamp. In country where high roads intersect, join hands with your allies. Do not linger in dangerously isolated positions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We shall be unable to turn natural advantage to account unless we make use of local guides.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Too frequent rewards signify that the enemy is at the end of his resources; too many punishments betray a condition of dire distress.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Confront your soldiers with the deed itself; never let them know your design.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Move not unless you see an advantage; use not your troops unless there is something to be gained; fight not unless the position is critical. No ruler should put troops into the field merely to gratify his own spleen; no general should fight a battle simply out of pique.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But a kingdom that has once been destroyed can never come again into being; nor can the dead ever be brought back to life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In a war, the greatest victory is one that requires no battle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;siddhartha&#34;&gt;Siddhartha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can&amp;rsquo;t learn some things from other people but rather have to learn them by working hard yourself (the
age old tale of the caterpillar and the cocoon)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to be patient and willing to wait - waiting is a skill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is something to learn from everything&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not mine to judge another&amp;rsquo;s life - it is purely me that I should evaluate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When someone seeks; said Siddhartha, then it easily happens that his eyes see only the thing that he seeks, and he is able to find nothing, to take in nothing because he always thinks only about the thing he is seeking, because he has one goal, because he is obsessed with his goal. Seeking means: having a goal. But finding means: being free, being open, having no goal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are not going in circles, we are going upwards. The path is a spiral; we have already climbed many steps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.businessinsider.com/why-tim-ferriss-considers-the-novel-siddhartha-an-important-book-2016-12&#34;&gt;http://www.businessinsider.com/why-tim-ferriss-considers-the-novel-siddhartha-an-important-book-2016-12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;billions&#34;&gt;Billions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;when allowing a competitor to look at his trades. &amp;ldquo;Lots of guys watch bruce lee movies, doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you can do karate&amp;rdquo; - Axe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ray-dalio&#34;&gt;Ray Dalio&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decide what to do and &lt;em&gt;have the courage to do it&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Success is not a matter attaining one&amp;rsquo;s goals, it is the struggle of evolution towards attaining them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pain + reflection = progress and meditation is invaluable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1) know your goals and run after them 2) encounter problems in the way of getting to goals 3) diagnoze these problems to identify their root causes 4) design plan to eliminate them 5) execute those designs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First identify event type, then identify its behavior and outcomes, then tackle it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To get the most out of life, you have to take more risk. Have to balance risk and reward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our ego and blind spot barriers are the biggest ones we need to deal with. Be radically open minded&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We like to believe our own opinions because we like to be right more than we like knowing what&amp;rsquo;s true&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nobody alone can fully appreciate reality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace the joy of being proven right with the joy of knowing what&amp;rsquo;s true. Find the most thoughtful people who disagree with you. Point out the things you&amp;rsquo;d individually miss&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See beyond yourself and want others to be successful as well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>library</title>
      <link>http://avaid96.github.io/library/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 11:37:23 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://avaid96.github.io/library/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Exceptional books&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Siddhartha - Hermann Hesse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ascent of money - Nial Ferguson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ThinkTwice - Michael Mauboussin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One up on wall street - Peter Lynch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open - Andre Agassi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Art of war - Sun Tzu&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thinking fast and slow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Mother Tongue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Influence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reading-list&#34;&gt;Reading list&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Innovator&amp;rsquo;s dilemma&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;design of everyday things&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>about</title>
      <link>http://avaid96.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 23:38:42 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://avaid96.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a current senior at Northwestern University. I love learning, creating things and seeing new places and meeting new people.
I&amp;rsquo;m aiming to write about things that I learn, things that I create and just random thoughts and experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://avatars3.githubusercontent.com/u/9308841?v=3&amp;s=466&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; align=&#34;middle&#34;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny story, I first got into computer science because it was the only A/C classroom at my school.
Escaping the Mumbai heat, I found myself enjoying the logical way computer scientists think and building tangible products that could solve problems.
I&amp;rsquo;ve come a long way since then but not much has changed with respect to my curiousity, passion and excitement for learning new things, thinking,
solving hard problems and showing off about something I&amp;rsquo;ve built. Besides my passion for technology, I am keenly interested in studying people&amp;rsquo;s
choices through Economics and identifying opportunities using my financial skill set. I have a strongly
entrepreneurial mindset and a passion for building things to solve problems. To know more about my education, experiences and projects:
feel free to look at my &lt;a href=&#34;http://avaid96.github.io/cv.pdf&#34;&gt;CV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any interesting work that you think I&amp;rsquo;d like, feel free to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:avaid1996@gmail.com?Subject=I%20was%20on%20your%20blog%3A%20&#34;&gt;contact me&lt;/a&gt;. I am particularly interested in positions in product management&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>